<tool id="nc_score" name="nc_score" version="1.0.0">
  <description>nc.score: similarity measure is an N-dimensional extension of the checkerboard score</description>
  <command interpreter="python">nc_score_galaxy_frontend.py
	--x $inputx
	#if $str($gchoice_y.global_y)  == "1":
			--y $inputy
	#end if	
	--bins  $bins
	--min_abundance $min_abundance
	--min_samples $min_samples

	--o_nc_score_results $o_nc_score_results
   </command>
	<inputs>
			<param format="ccrepe" name="inputx"  type="data" label="Input x dataset"  multiple="false"    help="Input x - Please upload using Get Data with format=ccrepe"/>
			
		<conditional name="gchoice_y">
        	<param name="global_y" type="select" label="Use a second dataframe containing the relative abundances in cavity2" >
        		<option value="0" selected='True'>No</option>
				<option value="1">Yes</option>
        	</param>
           	<when value="0">
			</when>

        	<when value="1">
			     <param format="ccrepe" name="inputy"  type="data" label="Input y dataset"  multiple="false"    help="Input y - Please upload using Get / Data with format=ccrepe"/>
			</when>
        </conditional>
			
		<param name="bins" type="integer" size="4" value="5" min="0" label="Bins"  help="Number of bins to use  "/>
		
		<param name="min_abundance" type="float" size="6" value="0.0001" min="0" label="min.abundance" 
		help="Minimum abundance threshold for quality control filtering.  For a feature to be included, it must take a value of at least  min.abundance  in at least min.samples  percent of samples."/>

		<param name="min_samples" type="float" size="6" value="0.1" min="0" label="min.samples" 
		help="Minimum sample threshold for quality control filtering.  For a feature to be included, it must take a value of at least min.abundance in at least min.samplespercent of samples."/>

		
		
		Minimum sample threshold for quality control filtering.  For a feature to be included, it must take a value of at least \Rcode{min.abundance} in at least \Rcode{min.samples} percent of samples.

		
    </inputs>

	<outputs>
            <data  name="o_nc_score_results"  format="ccrepe_nc_score_results"  />
	</outputs>
                                  
  <help>
Overview
========

**CCREPE** is a package for analysis of sparse compositional data.  Specifically, it determines the *significance of association between features in a composition*, using any similarity measure (e.g. Pearson correlation, Spearman correlation, etc.)  The CCREPE methodology stands for Compositionality Corrected by Renormalization and Permutation, as detailed below.  The package also provides a novel similarity measure, the N-dimensional checkerboard score (NC-score), particularly appropriate to compositions derived from microbial community sequencing data.  This results in p-values and false discovery rate q-values corrected for the effects of compositionality. 

The package contains two functions:  **CCREPE**  and **NC.SCORE** and is maintained by the Huttenhower Lab. 

General functionality
=====================

**nc.score**  similarity measure is an N-dimensional extension of the checkerboard score particularly suited to similarity score calculations between compositions derived from ecological relative abundance measurements.

In such cases, features typically represent species abundances, and the NC-score discretizes these continuous values into one of N bins before computing a normalized similarity of co-occurrence or co-exclusion.

This can be used as a standalone function or with ccrepe as above to obtain compositionality-corrected p-values.

The NC-score is an extension to Diamond's checkerboard scoreto ordinal data. 

The generalization of the checkerboard score is through defining general co-variation and co-exclusion patterns in ordinal data. 

Input
=====

The package can accepts either one input (**x**)  or two inputs (**x and y**)  which are  files in table format.

Please load them into Galaxy using the Get-Data / Upload File and **be sure to select File Format = ccrepe** 


Outputs
=======

nc.score  generates a file with the similarity scores

Sample Files:
=============

Two sample files can be downloaded from:

https://bitbucket.org/biobakery/galaxy_ccrepe/wiki/ant.narix.txt    

**and**

https://bitbucket.org/biobakery/galaxy_ccrepe/wiki/p.fornix.txt   

Please upload them using Galaxy's Get-Data and assign them file-format **ccrepe**


 
  </help>
</tool>
